We continue to study the LaTex system. In the previous lecture we have learned
how to type formulas, add pictures and make tables.
However, LaTex’ functionality is obviously not limited to this, and today we are going
to consider a group of useful options for your further work with this system.
Let’s start with the layout of the text. We
have already covered basic typing rules
before.
I would like to consider some
significant
aspects in more detail. The font
size can be set by the following commands –
from the smallest to the largest. The size of the main font
is set, as you remember, in class
file options, and its default
value is 10.
Different types of fonts such as serif,
sans serif, monospaced, semibold,
italic, oblique and small capital are set by the following commands.
I’d like to remind that text formatting commands change the current font to the
end of the current group, which is
specified by environment or braces.
However, font style can be set by commands with
arguments as follows.
The LaTeX system allows a finer adjustment of fonts if needed.
The system certainly allows you to type
various typographic characters including
letters
with diacritical characters, inherent in
various foreign languages,
punctuation marks, currency symbols, which implies importing specific packages, and so on.
To give a clear example, there are three types of dashes
dependent on its length: short, medium and long. Therefore, they can be typed by one,
two and three consecutive characters
respectively.
There are different types of quotes. Quotation marks are opened with two
inversed and closed with two regular
apostrophes in English.
In a Russian variation, as a rule, little spruces
are used, which are typed using “less” and “more” characters. As noted earlier,
LaTeX does not recognize the total amount of spaces and replaces all of them with only one
when compiling the source file. However, if you need to manually adjust spaces,
you can use the following commands
that specify fixed horizontal
intervals of different length.
We draw your attention to the negative space, which is often convenient to use in cases
when it is necessary to reduce the distance between characters.
In addition, there is a universal
command \hspace{}, which
allows you to specify the exact positive or negative value of the gap.
There is a similar set of commands
for adding vertical gaps, including
the \vspace{} command, which applies a specific value.
If you remember, one of the special characters that were mentioned earlier was a tilde.
So, this symbol is used in LaTeX to
specify a non-breaking space.
Let’s proceed directly to the organization of the text.
The title information of the work is
specified by a set
of appropriate environments
depending on the class of a document.
For example, there is a possibility to specify the title, authors and date in standard classes.
After that a title page is generated by the
\maketitle command.
However, in article templates there might
also be author affiliations, abstract, keywords and so on.
In the source file document division into sections can be done with the following
commands. The \tableofcontents command
allows you to automatically generate a table of contents of the document.
The section names and pages are updated during the
compilation.
Note that you can change the
default names of standard headings,
which are automatically assigned to the table of
contents, chapters, pictures, tables in LaTeX. It can be useful in document execution cases, for example,
in Russian in compliance with certain requirements.
LaTeX provides an ability to add lists with
different markers.
For example, unordered
lists are set by
the following construction.
Right after the \item command,
which is defining item in the list, an argument
can optionally be specified for a non-standard marker. An ordered list is compiled similarly
by the following environment. Please note that lists can be nested.
You can add tags to
specific items
and make links to them in
future in case of an ordered list.
Text footnotes are added using the \footnote command with the required
argument, which defines the text of the footnote. They are ordered.
If it is necessary to add a custom
index, it should be
indicated in square brackets. Since LaTeX is oriented towards
the layout of scientific literature, it allows to add
various mathematical environments to the document such as theorems,
lemmas, assumptions, proofs and more. They can be provided in advance inside
an article template
class file or declared in the
preamble of the source file.
If it is necessary to display
the inscription “as it is”, that is, verbatim, ignoring the special LaTeX characters,
then you can use the following environment by connecting the
appropriate package.
The whole text, which is
inside will be displayed in
a monospace font in the document. This option is convenient, for example, when displaying web links.
If you work with a large document consisting of several chapters - for example,
a dissertation, a report or a book - it is
convenient to divide the content of the
document
into several separate files and load
them by the following command during
compilation of the main file.
This functionality also assists in
collaboration work on the document, when each co-author works on the specific part
of their own, which can further be easily integrated into the main document
with automatic formulas ordering,
pictures, tables, links, literature and
everything else. Note that the preamble of the document can also be taken out into a separate file - partially or in full.
The uploaded files can be distributed to
subfolders.
In this case you have to specify
the path to each file.
Another useful option is the ability to place image files in a separate folder.
In this case you have to either specify the path to a file each
time you add a picture or specify the
path in the preamble
to each subfolder that contains images using the following command.
a journal or conference in your professional field, download a template for
LaTeX from thits website, and train your
layout skills this time more comprehensively
using what we have learned in this chapter.